Hi. Today, I'm going to take you through glimpses
مرحبا. اليوم، سأقوم بأخذكم في لمحات
of about eight of my projects,
لحوالي ثمانية من مشاريعي،
done in collaboration with Danish artist Soren Pors.
تمت بالتعاون مع الفنان الدانماركي سورين بورز.
We call ourselves Pors and Rao,
نسمي أنفسنا بورز وراو،
and we live and work in India.
ونعيش ونعمل في الهند.
I'd like to begin with my very first object,
أود البدء بأول مشروع لي،
which I call "The Uncle Phone."
والذي سميته "هاتف العم."
And it was inspired by my uncle's peculiar habit
وقد استلهمته من عادة عمي الغريبة
of constantly asking me to do things for him,
في الطلب مني القيام بأشياء من أجله،
almost like I were an extension of his body --
كما لو أنني امتداد لبدنه --
to turn on the lights or to bring him a glass of water,
لتشغيل النور أو احضار كأس ماء له،
a pack of cigarettes.
علبة سجائر.
And as I grew up, it became worse and worse,
وأنا أكبر، صار الأمر أسوء وأسوء،
And I started to think of it as a form of control.
وقد بدأت أفكر فيه كأنه نوع من التحكم.
But of course, I could never say anything,
لكن بالطبع، لم أستطع أبدا أن أقول شيئا،
because the uncle is a respected figure
لأن العم شخص محترم
in the Indian family.
في العائلة الهندية.
And the situation that irked me and mystified me the most
والوضعية التي أغضبتني وأدهشتني أكثر
was his use of a landline telephone.
هي استخدامه للهاتف الأرضي.
He would hold on to the receiver and expect me to dial a number for him.
يمسك بالسماعة ويتوقع مني أن أطلب له الرقم.
And so as a response and as a gift to my uncle,
وبالتالي كرد وكهدية لعمي،
I made him "The Uncle Phone."
صنعت له "هاتف العم."
It's so long that it requires two people to use it.
إنه طويل جدا بحيث يتطلب شخصين لاستخدامه.
It's exactly the way my uncle uses a phone that's designed for one person.
إنها تماما الطريقة التي يستخدم بها عمي الهاتف المصمم لشخص واحد.
But the problem is that, when I left home and went to college,
لكن المشكل أنه، حين خرجت من البيت وذهبت للجامعة،
I started missing his commands.
بدأت أفتقد أوامره.
And so I made him a golden typewriter
وبالتالي صنعت له آلة كاتبة ذهبية
through which he could dispense his commands
من خلالها يمكنه أن يوزع أوامره
to nephews and nieces around the world as an email.
على أبناء وبنات اخوانه حول العالم كرسالة إلكترونية.
So what he had to do was take a piece of paper, roll it into the carriage,
وبالتالي ما كان مطلوب منه القيام به هو أخذ ورقة ولفها في الحامل،
type his email or command and pull the paper out.
طبع رسالته أو أمره ثم سحب الورقة.
This device would automatically send the intended person
هذا الجهاز سيقوم أوتوماتيكيا بإرسال الرسالة كبريد إلكتروني
the letter as an email.
إلى الشخص المعني.
So here you can see, we embedded a lot of electronics
وبالتالي هنا يمكنكم أن تروا، قد دمجنا الكثير من الإلكترونيات
that understands all of the mechanical actions
التي تفهم كل تلك الحركات الميكانيكية
and converts it to digital.
وتحولها إلى رقمية.
So my uncle is only dealing with a mechanical interface.
وبالتالي عمي يتعامل فقط مع الواجهة الميكانيكية.
And of course, the object had to be very grand and have a sense of ritualism,
وبالطبع، فإن الشيئ وجب أن يكون كبيرا ويوفر نوعا من الطقوسية،
the way my uncle likes it.
بالطريقة التي تعجب عمي.
The next work is a sound-sensitive installation
العمل التالي هو تثبيت حساس للصوت
that we affectionately call "The Pygmies."
والذي نسميه بمودة "الأقزام."
And we wanted to work with a notion of being
وأردنا أن نشتغل بمبدأ كوننا
surrounded by a tribe of very shy, sensitive and sweet creatures.
محاطين بقبيلة من المخلوقات الخجولة للغاية والحساسة واللطيفة.
So how it works is we have these panels, which we have on the wall,
إذن فالطريقة التي يشتغل بها هو أننا نتوفر على هذه اللوحات، والتي وضعناها على الحائط،
and behind them, we have these little creatures which hide.
ووراءها، لدينا هذه المخلوقات الصغيرة التي تختبئ.
And as soon as it's silent, they sort of creep out.
وبمجرد أن يعم الصمت، تقوم نوعا ما بالزحف خارجا.
And if it's even more silent, they stretch their necks out.
وإن كانت أكثر صمتا، يمدون أعناقهم خارجا.
And at the slightest sound, they hide back again.
وبسماع أدنى صوت، يختبئون مجددا.
So we had these panels on three walls of a room.
وبالتالي كانت لدينا هذه الألواح في ثلاثة جدران من الغرفة.
And we had over 500 of these little pygmies hiding behind them.
وكان لدينا أكثر من 500 من هذه الأقزام مختبئة خلفها.
So this is how it works.
وبالتالي إليكم طريقة عملها.
This is a video prototype.
هذا نموذج فيديو أولي.
So when it's quiet, it's sort of coming out from behind the panels.
وبالتالي حين يعم الهدوء، تخرج نوعا ما من وراء الألواح.
And they hear like humans do, or real creatures do.
وتسمع مثلما يفعل البشر، أو تفعل الكائنات الحقيقية.
So they get immune to sounds that scare them after awhile.
فإنهم يكونون مناعة من الأصوات التي تخيفهم بعد مدة.
And they don't react to background sounds.
ولا يتفاعلون مع أصوات الخلفية.
You'll hear a train in moment that they don't react to.
ستسمعون قطارا بعد لحظات لا يتفاعلون معه.
(Noise)
(ضجيج)
But they react to foreground sounds. You'll hear that in a second.
لكنهم يتفاعلون مع أصوات المقدمة. ستسمعون ذلك في ثانية.
(Whistling)
(صفير)
So we worked very hard
وبالتالي اشتغلنا بجهد كبير
to make them as lifelike as possible.
لجعلها نابضة بالحياة بقدر الإمكان.
So each pygmy has its own behavior, psyche,
وبالتالي كل قزم له سلوك خاص به، نفسية،
mood swings, personalities and so on.
تقلب مزاج، شخصية وما إلى ذلك.
So this is a very early prototype.
وبالتالي هذا نموذج أولي مبكر.
Of course, it got much better after that.
بالطبع، تحسن كثيرا بعد ذلك.
And we made them react to people,
وجعلناها تتفاعل مع الناس،
but we found that people were being quite playful and childlike with them.
لكننا وجدنا أن الناس يكونون لعوبين وكالأطفال معهم.
This is a video installation called "The Missing Person."
هذا تثبيت فيديو يدعى "الشخص المفقود."
And we were quite intrigued
وقد كنا مفتونين للغاية
with playing with the notion of invisibility.
باللعب على مبدئ التخفي.
How would it be possible to experience a sense of invisibility?
كيف قد يكون ممكنا تجربة حس التخفي؟
So we worked with a company
وبالتالي اشتغلنا مع شركة
that specializes in camera surveillance,
والتي تتخصص في المراقبة بالكاميرا،
and we asked them to develop a piece of software with us,
وطلبنا منهم أن يطوروا لنا برمجية،
using a camera
باستخدام كاميرا
that could look at people in the room, track them
والتي بإمكانها النظر إلى الناس في الغرفة وتعقبهم
and replace one person with the background, rendering them invisible.
وتعويض شخص واحد بالخلفية، وجعله غير مرئي.
So I'm just going to show you a very early prototype.
إذن سأعرض عليكم نموذج أولي مبكر.
On the right side you can see my colleague Soren,
في الجهة اليمنى يمكنكم رؤية زميلي سورين،
who's actually in the space.
والذي هو بالفعل في الفضاء.
And on the left side, you'll see the processed video
وفي الجهة اليسرى، سترون الفيديو المعالج
where the camera has made him invisible.
حيث جعلته الكاميرا غير مرئي.
Soren enters the room. Pop! He goes invisible.
سورين دخل الغرفة. بوب! تحول إلى شيئ غير مرئي.
And you can see that the camera is tracking him and erasing.
ويكنكم رؤية أن الكاميرا تتعقبه وتمحوه.
It's a very early video,
إنه فيديو أولي جدا.
so we haven't yet dealt with the overlap and all of that,
لذلك لم نكن قد تعاملنا مع التداخل وكل ذلك،
but that got refined pretty soon, later.
لكن ذلك تحسن قريبا جدا، لاحقا.
So how we used it was in a room where we had a camera looking into the space,
والطريقة التي استخدمناه بها هو أنه كان في غرفة حيث كان لدينا كاميرا تنظر إلى الفضاء،
and we had one monitor, one on each wall.
وكان لدينا شاشة على كل جدار.
And as people walked into the room,
وبمشي الناس في الغرفة،
they would see themselves in the monitor, except with one difference:
سيرون أنفسهم على الشاشة، باستثناء فرق واحد:
one person was constantly invisible
شخص واحد كان مختفيا دائما
wherever they moved in the room.
أينما تحركوا في الغرفة.
So this is a work called "The Sun Shadow."
هذا عمل يطلق عليه "ظل الشمس."
And it was almost like a sheet of paper,
وقد كان تقريبا مثل ورقة،
like a cutout of a childlike drawing
مثل تقطيع لرسم طفولي
of an oil spill or a sun.
لبقعة نفط أو شمس.
And from the front, this object appeared to be very strong and robust,
ومن الأمام، يظهر هذا الشيء قويا جدا ومتينا،
and from the side, it almost seemed very weak.
ومن الجانب، يظهر وكأنه ضعيف جدا.
So people would walking into the room and they'd almost ignore it,
لذلك فالناس يسيرون في الغرفة وقد يتجاهلونه تقريبا،
thinking it was some crap laying around.
معتقدين أنه فقط قمامة مرمية على الأرض.
But as soon as they passed by,
لكن بمجرد أن يمروا بجانبه،
it would start to climb up the wall in jerky fashion.
يبدأ في تسلق الحائط بطريقة متشنجة.
And it would get exhausted, and it would collapse every time.
وسيشعر بالتعب، وينهار كل مرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this work
إذن فهذا يشتغل
is a caricature of an upside-down man.
إنه كاريكاتير لرجل رأسا على عقب.
His head is so heavy, full of heavy thoughts,
رأسه ثقيل جدا، مليء بأفكار ثقيلة،
that it's sort of fallen into his hat,
لدرجة أنه يسقط نوعا ما في قبعته،
and his body's grown out of him almost like a plant.
وجسده قد نبت منه وكأنه نبتة.
Well what he does is he moves around
ما يقوم به هو أنه يتحرك
in a very drunken fashion on his head
بطريقة مترنحة على رأسه
in a very unpredictable and extremely slow movement.
بحركة لا يمكن التنبؤ بها وفي غاية البطء.
And it's kind of constrained by that circle.
وهو نوعا ما مقيد بتلك الدائرة.
Because if that circle weren't there, and the floor was very even,
لأنه إن لم تكن تلك الدائرة هناك، وكان السطح في غاية الاستواء،
it would start to wander about in the space.
سيبدأ في التجول في الفضاء.
And there's no wires.
وليس هناك أسلاك.
So I'll just show you an instance --
إذن سأريكم مثالا --
so when people enter the room, it activates this object.
إذن حين يدخل الناس إلى الغرفة، يتم تفعيل الشيء.
And it very slowly, over a few minutes,
وببطء شديد، على مدى بضع دقائق،
sort of painfully goes up,
يصعد بطريقة مؤلمة نوعا ما،
and then it gains momentum
وثم يكتسب قوة دافعة
and it looks like it's almost about to fall.
ويبدو وكأنه تقريبا على وشك السقوط.
And this is an important moment,
وهذه لحظة مهمة،
because we wanted to instill in the viewer
لأننا أردنا أن نغرس في المشاهد
an instinct to almost go and help, or save the subject.
غريزة أن يذهب ويساعد، أو ينقذه.
But it doesn't really need it,
لكنه لا يحتاج ذلك حقا،
because it, again, sort of manages to pull itself up.
لأنه، مجددا، يستطيع أن يرفع نفسه نوعا ما.
So this work was a real technical challenge for us,
وهذا العمل كان تحديا تقنيا حقيقيا لنا،
and we worked very hard, like most of our works, over years
وقد اشتغلنا بشق الأنفس، مثل معظم أعمالنا، على مدى سنوات
to get the mechanics right and the equilibrium and the dynamics.
لجعل الميكانيكا صحيحة وتحقيق توازن الحركية.
And it was very important for us
وقد كانت في غاية الأهمية لنا
to establish the exact moment that it would fall,
أن نعين اللحظة الدقيقة التي سيسقط فيها،
because if we made it in a way that it would topple over,
لأنه إن جعلناه بطريقة ما بحيث يسقط،
then it would damage itself,
فإنه قد يؤذي نفسه،
and if it didn't fall enough, it wouldn't instill that fatalism,
وإن لم يسقط بما فيه الكفاية، لن يوحي بتلك القدرية،
or that sense of wanting to go and help it.
أو الشعور بالرغبة في مساعدته.
So I'm going to show you a very quick video
إذن سأعرض عليكم فيديو سريع
where we are doing a test scenario -- it's much faster.
حيث نقوم بسيناريو تجريبي -- إنه أكثر سرعة بكثير.
That's my colleague. He's let it go.
هذا زميلي. لقد أطلقه.
Now he's getting nervous, so he's going to go catch it.
الآن يشعر بالعصبية، وبالتالي سيذهب للامساك به.
But he doesn't need to,
لكنه لا يحتاج ذلك،
because it manages to lift itself up on its own.
لأنه يدبر رفع نفسه بنفسه.
So this is a work that we were very intrigued with,
إذن فهذا عمل كنا في مفتونين به،
working with the aesthetic of fur
العمل مع جمالية الفراء
embedded with thousands of tiny different sizes
مضمنة بآلاف الأحجام الصغيرة المختلفة
of fiber optics, which twinkle like the night sky.
من الألياف الضوئية، والتي تتلألأ مثل السماء ليلا.
And it's at the scale of the night sky.
وهي بمقياس السماء ليلا.
So we wrapped this around a blob-like form,
وهكذا قمنا بلف هذه على شكل يشبه فقاعة،
which is in the shape of a teddy bear,
والتي هي على شكل دمية دب،
which was hanging from the ceiling.
والذي كان معلقا على السطح.
And the idea was to sort of contrast
والفكرة كانت أن نباين نوعا ما
something very cold and distant and abstract like the universe
شيئا باردا للغاية وبعيدا وتجريديا مثل الكون
into the familiar form of a teddy bear,
في شكل اعتيادي مثل دمية الدب،
which is very comforting and intimate.
والتي هي مريحة وحميمية.
And the idea was that at some point
والفكرة كانت أنه في مرحلة ما
you would stop looking at the form of a teddy bear
ستتوقف عن النظر إلى شكل دمية الدب
and you would almost perceive it to be a hole in the space,
وستميزها تقريبا على أنها حفرة في الفضاء،
and as if you were looking out into the twinkling night sky.
وكما لو أنك تنظر إلى سماء ليلية وامضة.
So this is the last work, and a work in progress,
وهذا هو آخر عمل، وهو في طور الانجاز،
and it's called "Space Filler."
ويدعى "حاشي الفضاء."
Well imagine a small cube that's about this big
حسنا، تخيلوا مكعبا صغيرا بهذا القدر
standing in front of you in the middle of the room,
واقفا أمامك في وسط الغرفة،
and as you approached it, it tried to intimidate you
وبمجرد أن تقترب منه، حاول تخويفك
by growing into a cube
بالنمو إلى مكعب
that's twice its height and [eight] times its volume.
هو بضعف ارتفاعه وأربعة أضعاف حجمه.
And so this object is constantly expanding and contracting
وبالتالي هذا الشيء يتمدد ويتقلص باستمرار
to create a dynamic with people moving around it --
لخلق ديناميكية مع الناس الذين يتحركون من حوله --
almost like it were trying
وكأنه يحاول نوعا ما
to conceal a secret within its seams or something.
اخفاء سر داخل لحاماته أو ما شابه.
So we work with a lot of technology,
وبالتالي نشتغل بتكنولوجيا كثيرة،
but we don't really love technology,
لكننا لا نحب التكنولوجيا فعلا،
because it gives us a lot of pain in our work over years and years.
لأنها تسبب لنا الكثير من الوجع في عملنا على مر السنين.
But we use it because we're interested
لكننا نستخدمها لأننا مهتمون
in the way that it can help us
بالطريقة التي يمكن أن تساعدنا بها
to express the emotions and behavioral patterns
في التعبير عن أنماط المشاعر والسلوكات
in these creatures that we create.
في هذه الكائنات التي نبدع.
And once a creature pops into our minds,
وبمجرد أن يتبادر إلى ذهننا مخلوق،
it's almost like the process of creation
وكأنها تقريبا عملية إبداع
is to discover the way this creature really wants to exist
هو اكتشاف الطريقة التي يريد بها هذا المخلوق فعلا أن يوجد
and what form it wants to take and what way it wants to move.
والشكل الذي يريد أن يتخذه والطريقة التي يريد التحرك بها.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)